Welcome to the lecture on installing a Sensu dashboard.
Would you believe that out of the box Sensu doesn't come with a dashboard?
Surprised?
You shouldn't be.
Remember Sensu's all about flexibility and modularized components that to do one thing well.
It's refreshing to me that Sensu doesn't provide a dashboard
because that means that it's API is well formed
and ready to integrate with any kind of external component that you might need
including a dashboard or a CLI or something custom.
in other words Sensu's decoupling philosophy means that you can use any kind of external component
including something in-house and it will work.
If you've got something fancy you want to integrate Sensu with, go for it.
The Sensu API is well constructed and easy to integrate with.
For most people, using the standard, open source Uchiwa dashboard works well for them.
So that's what we'll do in this lecture.
The official Sensu documentation
references two different dashboards:
Uchiwa, which is the open sourced version
and then there's Sensu Enterprise Dashboard, that's the proprietary Version.
Being an introductory course we're gonna stick with the open source one.
The enterprise one has more
advanced features
for things like LDAP and fancy fine grained access controls,
but we won't need these for this introductory video.
If you are interested in the enterprise dashboard there is a later lecture
that will cover all the differences between the enterprise and open-source offerings.
Let's go ahead and install Uchiwa.
Uchiwa is available from the existing Sensu repositories you've already enabled.
So it's very easy to install.
Let's take a look at the actual package.
It's got some files, but take a look you can see the source code, it is in Go.
The frontend is in javascript,
and then there's the binary.
Let's look at the configuration file that it provided for us.
As you can see it's hinting here that Uchiwa is designed to be multi-site aware.
You could declare multiple sites and Uchiwa will provide that kind of
single pane of glass to show you all of them together.
This is pretty handy as you scale out Sensu to monitor multiple data centers or multiple regions.
It's pretty handy.
For this introductory course we only have one site just localhost so we don't need this second one.
This entry here represents the actually API endpoint.
For us this is the localhost.
And "site1" is fine, I'm just gonna call it also localhost.
you should take note here that the default binding is on all IPs, on port 3000.
And if it wasn't obvious, it is HTTP.
Ok, let's go ahead and start Uchiwa.
You saw that it listens on port 3000 so let's see if we can load it in our web browser.
It's not working.
Well, let's do some troubleshooting.
Is Uchiwa running?
It isn't.
Let's look at the logs
The log for Uchiwa is in /var/log/
There's an "uchiwa.er" and a "uchiwa.log".
Looks like there's some contents of "uchiwa.log" so let's look at that.
JSON output again
Here's the smoking gun:
"couldn't read uchiwa.json decoding the file."
remember when I said that JSON is for machines and humans aren't very good at
editing them?  Well, it's true.
Here's a good opportunity to use that "jq" command again: "jq . uchiwa.json"
Here it gives a closer error here is line 9, column 3. So let's take a look at that...
Although it's pretty subtle the
error here is that I have a trailing comma.
And now it prints out ok. Let's try to start it again.
Let's just check that it is actually running.
It is.
And we're back up.
Let's take a look at our API endpoints here.
We have one endpoint, in Uchiwa the front end is described as data centers.
It is connected.
We have one client, "mycoolhost" from when we originally set up the client.
And we have a check, that memory check that we set up originally.
In the next lecture we'll cover the ins and outs of Uchiwa in more depth,
but for now this is the basic installation and troubleshooting of Uchiwa.