Hi and welcome to the screencast on installing and configuring RabbitMQ.
If you remember from our architecture diagram RabbitMQ is the central message bus
between the Sensu server and the Sensu Client.
So we have to get it setup first before we can really do much of anything in Sensu.
So that's what we'll do.
I'm mostly going to be following the guidelines of the official Sensu documentation.
I'm doing this because this is an introductory course, so it's likely you'll have kind of a stock setup
with no previous installation.
I'm going to be following the guidelines kind of verbatim,
so let's do it.
First we'll start by installing Erlang.
if you didn't know RabbitMQ is written in Erlang so it requires the Erlang virtual machine.
We're going to be installing from the official sources.
We'll speed pass the installation here
You may not technically need the most latest and greatest version of Erlang and RabbitMQ
but it's recommended.
There's always the trade-off of course between using the latest versions from
external sources versus the stable
versions from the distro but
they may be outdated.
The official docs do recommend using the latest versions so that's what we do here in this video.
And now that we have Erlang installed, we'll install RabbitMQ.
Again we're using the official upstream repositories.
To get the latest version.
Of course if you already have a RabbitMQ installation
you're absolutely free to use it.
Sensu doesn't really mind where it gets
RabbitMQ as long as it's available.
Of course for this introduction video we're going to be just using our local server to host RabbitMQ,
but it could very easily be a remote
installation or an existing RabbitMQ cluster.
Again this is one of the nice things
about Sensu is because it's modular
if you need to scale out your RabbitMQ separately from your Sensu cluster you can.
And of course you can reuse RabbitMQ
for your own purposes as well.
Per the docs, we'll make it start on default and we'll start it up.
RabbitMQ is kind of like Apache in the sense that is has vhosts
that allow you to segregate different queues and different
exchanges to different users.
So per the official documentation we are going to make a Sensu RabbitMQ vhost.
And we'll give that Sensu user permissions
We'll make it a Sensu user and give it permissions user and get permissions to that vhost.
That's all there is for the official documentation on RabbitMQ.
I'd like to give you a little bit more information about
RabbitMQ in case you've never run it before.
RabbitMQ is it's own things own thing, it's got it's own docs, it's own
scaling properties, it's own failure modes,
but you should at least be aware of where the logs are.
The logs are in the place you'd expect them to be:
/var/log/rabbitmq/
It's got a couple different logs for different of things but the main log is going to be this one here.
Not much to report yet, but you'll see more when we start up Sensu and it starts communicating.
Very common errors occur when there's a
mismatch between the Sensu configuration
for RabbitMQ and RabbitMQ's
configuration.
For example: usernames and password and vhosts and that kind of thing.
RabbitMQ also has a web interface
which is nice to have in some situations.
It's good to have some visualization
into what's going on behind the scenes
there's a little more work to enable it,
but you can enable the RabbitMQ management plugin.
Now because I'm using your Vagrant I have to make
a separate SSH tunnel to get localhost access because
by default it's only available using the guest user with localhost
and then you can just open up localhost:15672
the management port in your web broser and then you can use the guest account.
username is guest
password is guest
And you can see that there's not much going on again, there's
just installed, so nothings actually happen here
but it's good to know that this exists so you can see what's going on
That's about it for RabbitMQ. Again
there's not much going on more not so it's not much to see
but once we install Sensu you'll see messages flowing in here.
I have additional information on the lecture
notes regarding the official
documentation and the steps and commands I ran in this.
Again they mostly mirror from what the official Sensu documentation has
but that's about it for RabbitMQ.