So far in these lectures we've been
mostly following the official documentation on
installing and configuring Sensu,
which is cool.
But let's see if we can go a little bit
beyond the docs
and try to get our Sensu installation to do something a little more useful.
In particular, let's try to make it send us an email.
If you remember from the architecture lecture the job of the Sensu server component
is to respond to events and act on them.
These actions are in the form of
handlers.
In Sensu, a handler is a script that does something based on the event data
that comes from standard in.
This makes them pretty easy to write, test
and understand.
Remember our "cat" handler from our original installation?
Let's take a look at it's configuration.
The cat handler takes data from standard in but just echoes it right back out.
This isn't a very interesting handler but it does demonstrate what
handlers are supposed to do.
If we're going to do something more useful than just cat
we need to find a handler to do that useful thing.
In this case, email.
Now where would we go to find a Sensu email handler?
We could certainly write our own,
but
luckily on the internet, there's a collection of community Sensu plug-ins for you to use
here at the Sensu-plugins-github project and there are many many to choose from.
You do not have to reinvent the wheel when it comes to this
Let's type in "mail" and see what comes up.
We've got:
sensu-plugins-mailer
Sounds legit.
sensu-plugins-qmail is probably for checking qmail not for sending email.
sensu-plugins-ponymailer happens to be this
more advanced email handler that uses the "pony" rubygem.
This (sensu-plugins-mailer) is probably fine for us.
The sensu-plugins-mailer
you can see what it provides; a few different variations on the mailer,
gives you some example configuration,
links for install and setup.
This is probably what we want.
The first thing you should notice is that this thing is a Rubygem.
If you're already familiar with Rubygems, you probably feel right at home and already know what to do,
but not everybody is though and this is introductory course,
so let's figure out how we're gonna install this Rubygem.
Certainly you could do what it suggests right away which is just "gem install".
But, remember earlier when I talked about how Sensu
is packaged via an omnibus package?
Meaning that it comes with its own Ruby interpreter.
This is pretty convenient for us because it means that we don't have to install
yet another ruby on the system.
And who knows what version of Ruby it's going to be installing on the system-ruby?
If we can re-use Sensu's Ruby, let's do that.
It will give us a consistent version of Ruby across all platforms.
It's guaranteed to be there
already.
Seems to make sense to use this already.
But let's refresh our memory
about where Sensu puts its omnibus Ruby.
It's in /opt/sensu/embedded/bin/ and then this bin folder has the binaries
including the ruby interpreter and the gem command.
Well, let's use these to install our script.
Instead of running "gem install"
and this documentation here is just generic
documentation
so they just have sensu-plugins-disks.
Let's go back to our plugin here
sensu-plugin-mailer
Instead of running just "gem install"
We'll run
this gem install which is   "/opt/sensu/embedded/bin/gem install"
And then the name of the gem which is
"sensu-plugins-mailer"
Didn't work!
Didn't work because of FilePermissionError that's because the
omnibus package is a system package so everything is owned by root.
So you do have to run this with sudo
You have to run this in sudo because you need these to be installed as root
Ok. Still didn't work. let's work through it.
I couldn't find g++.
I happen to know that in order to build many things
on an Ubuntu system you need the build-essential package.
So let's just install that.
Ok. Now we can re-run that command
It finished.
But, where did it put it?
Instead of install you can use "gem contents"
to see the contents of a gem
and where they are installed on the file system.
You can see that they're in
/opt/sensu/embedded/lib/
But this would be the normal location where rubygems would be installed but they're in this special
omnibus gem install location place.
But when you install a gem the binaries end up in the bin folder of the ruby home.
That is in the same place we were before.
"ls /opt/sensu/embedded/bin"
and now you'll see some new scripts.
Let me filter them out.
you can see that the "gem install" installed these scripts for us to use
and they're just wrappers to actually execute the binary code in the gem itself.
So we're interested in this one (handler.mailer.rb)
Let's also, while we're in here, take a look at the file itself.
This is a very typical binstub of a gem install.
The important thing I want to point out is
this up here,
you can see that the shebang of this script
already references the embedded omnibus sensu ruby.
So if we just call this script directly it will
automatically use the embedded
Ruby that Sensu comes with, which is
excellent because that's exactly what we wanted.
It has no dependence on the sysem Ruby.
You would not want to run this with
the Ruby command in front, cause then you're not controlling which Ruby it's using.
By letting it use the shebang it's going to use the omnibus Ruby as intended.
Well, does it work? Let's try running it.
What do you think is happening?
No news, is good news?
Well, watch when I press Ctrl+D
You can see it was expecting some sort of JSON text.
Again, handlers operate on event data coming in from standard in.
So while we ran it, it was just waiting for the event data to appear .
It's not really going to do much here but if you have some event data that you could just
pipe to it, you could just kind of simulate it and test it.
That's ok.
It does seem to work. It runs, but
we'll need to do a more comprehensive test to see if it will actually email us.
So. let's configure it.
We already have this default_handler.json".
Remember, this is the cat command that we used before.
Well, instead of cat, let's run our handler.
Seems simple enough,
but the documentation did reference some configuration that we'd need:
Here are the docs for handler-mailer-mailgun.  That's not what we're using.
handler-mailer-ses is not what we're using.
handler-mailer is what we're using so we'll need this.
But, these docs aren't really saying where we should put it.
We can put this in this mailer.json file.
But remember that Sensu's configuration is all merged into one big
configuration dictionary based on files on disk in the "conf.d" folder.
So we can just take this example configuration language
and put it right here in the same file and Sensu doesn't really care,
but it's nice for us humans to see the configuration for a handler
live right next to the definition of a handler.
Now, you have to be really careful here because this is JSON and it's pretty easy for humans to mix-up.
But this is totally fine.
Again Sensu doesn't care how you organize your JSON files
because it globs them all together.
Let's adjust this configuration to meet our needs.
The admin GUI is just the link that the email will contain to point you to the
web interface of your choice.  We're using Uchiwa and for us that's http://localhost:3000
Obviously, in a production environment
you'd set your admin GUI to something different.
Let's make the mail appear to be from "sensu@localhost"
Let's email just "root@localhost"
We don't have a set SMTP server, just use localhost.
And again the domain "localhost" for our testing.
Obviously in a real environment you'd have your own SMTP configuration you'd want to use.
Let's save it.
Well, now what?
We've edited some configuration, now we
need to restart Sensu to get it to pickup on it.
But which component do we need to restart?
We're not using a configuration management tool so we're going to have to figure this out by hand.
But, if you remember the architecture, handlers are executed by the Sensu server,
so the only component that picks up on this particular kind of configuration is the Sensu server.
Let's restart the Sensu server and see what happens.
Let's watch the logs
Nothing really interesting.
Is it working?
Try to think back about the Uchiwa lecture
and think to yourself
"why am I not seen any email or any log lines pertaining about emails?"
Of course, Sensu's not a greenlight dashboard.
So there isn't anything failing and because there's no failing events, no handlers are going to be executed.
Well, let's make it interesting;
let's make the check fail,
that way we'll get a handler to be
executed and hopefully get some email.
Our only check in this example is the
check-mem.sh thing.
Let's make this one fail all the time
by making it just "exit 2"
Remember that Sensu uses the same protocol as Nagios
and "exit 2" indicates a critical failure
Now, which do we restart in this situation?
This is a subscription check so it goes out to all the subscribers subscribing to test.
So it seems like we would restart the Sensu server and you'd be right.
We do have to
restart the Sensu server in this case.
Let's watch the Sensu client's log and see how it reacts.
The Sensu Client is receiving check requests with a command of "exit 2"
That's good.
But look really carefully, the Sensu Client is
publishing a check result
but it's still executing our old check-mem
This behavior is surprising.
It's an artifact of the fact that we have the Sensu client and the Sensu server co-located on the same host.
If a Sensu client sees a check definition in its configuration
it will assume that the check definition contains specific overrides
that are designed to take precedence over the generic check-mem that comes from the server.
For example, if you imagine if you have a fleet of servers
with a lot of different memory capabilities and you have a special server that has a lot of RAM,
you might set a different threshold on
that
and set up a specific check-mem configuration on that client
to take precedence over what the server's asking you to run.
This can be a little confusing in this case because the Sensu client is on the same server.
So in this case we do have to restart the Sensu client
to get it to reload that configuration
file that we edited.
On other Sensu clients that don't have this configuration file on disk
they would not have to be reloaded.
Let's take a look at the logs.
Ok. Now it's receiving the check with a
command  of "exit 2"
and its publishing
an output of exit 2
You can see that it's return code is actually 2.
And the command I ran was "exit 2" so now it's working.
Well, is the Sensu server emailing us?
Let's look at these logs really carefully.
The Sensu server is publishing a check request for memory
with a command of "exit 2"
We saw just a second ago that the Sensu client is responding to that check request.
Here the Sensu server is processing an event.
Here's the check.
So it is processing it
and now we have the handler output.
Our handler and here's the command "handler-mailer" so that's good
output: "only handling every 180 occurances"
So it is getting the event
but by default this handler is only executing something
every 180 occurrences.
Occurrences is how many times this check has failed.
It's a filtering mechanism to make sure you don't get an email every 30 seconds.
How many occurrences have we had?
Well it says it right there in the event data.
It's happened five times; this check has been failing five times in a row
and this handler only operates every 180 occurrences.
So we might have to wait a while before we actually get an email out
Presumably it tries to do something on the first occurrences, the first occurrence.
well there's lots of things you can do to fine tune this filter
but I'm know a way that we can make this happen right now.
We can use each Uchiwa.
Here's that memory check.
I can manually resolve this check right now.
A manual resolve will make it go
away for just a second
but our Sensu Client is still running the "exit 2"
and it's come back now.
But it did reset the occurrences back to 0.
So our handler probably did something.
It's a little messy to read because it's in JSON format but look carefully.
The handler did do something and its output is unfortunately stack trace.
But look at this "Connection refused"
Pretty hard to read,
but the reason it's happening is because it could not connect to
the mail server that I asked it to
connect to which was localhost:25
That's because this is a vagrant box and it doesn't come with
anything out of the box so we're gonna have to install mail server.
Let's take a look at the log again.
It's still doing things,
but it's being filtered.
Let's do the manual resolve trick again to force a reset.
Here you can see the handler actually did something.
sent alert for mycoolhost/memory to root@localhost
And it did it again.
That first one was for the manual resolve; the second one was for the first alert.
Well, let's read it.
You get a resolve and alert.
Let's take a look at the alert.
There it is.
Not much to see because "exit 2" doesn't produce any kind of output,
but "2" represents critical, it's happened one time.
You get an email on the first time.
Here's a convenient link to the GUI that we just had opened: Uchiwa.
Here's the email with that recovery.
Status: OK
It happened 12 times by the time it resolved, no big deal.
Obviously, we've just scratched the surface here
but at least you have a Sensu installation that can email you
which is not bad.
There are many more things you can
do.
There's tons of community handlers out there,
ranging from Slack to IRC to anything you
can think of.
And remember, you can write your own.
All they do is take something
from standard in and act on it.
Check out the external links section of this lecture for show notes
and links to the documentation on handlers for more reading
and also all the commands I used in this lecture.