Hi.  Welcome to Sensu: An introduction.
My name is Kyle.  I'm an engineer.
I build systems for a living.  I run Sensu in production.  I get paged for it; I get paged for
all the systems I build.  I care about them
and I want to build systems that I can
be proud of.
I'm proud of the Sensu infrastructure I've built. I'd like to share that with you.  Throughout
this course I'll be teaching mostly the
open source version of Sensu,
although I will cover the differences
between the open source enterprise
version, if you're interested in that.  I hope
that you are also an engineer who wants
to build good systems and whether you're
installing a monitoring system from scratch
where you currently don't have a monitoring system or if you're replacing an
existing centralized monitoring with a modern one like
Sensu, both of these use cases are
covered in this introductory course.  I also hope
that you'll share my enthusiasm
about Sensu's architecture and
flexibility.
These to me are the two key points that make
Sensu different compared to all the
other monitoring systems out there.  So sit
back, take some notes, get a server
running and walk with me through
installing and configuring Sensu for
the first time.  I hope you enjoy it!