Welcome to the first lecture on
installing Sensu, but before we get
started on installing or configuring any
files, the first thing we need to cover
is the architecture.  Sensu's unique
architecture is one of the most
confusing or maybe new things about Sensu that people get wrong as a beginner.
It's important when you're discovering
or learning about the system for the
first time that you get a really good
grasp of how Sensu actually works in
the background because that mental model
helps you understand the system and its
failure modes.  It also helps you take
advantage of the good parts about Sensu;
taking advantage of flexibility and
designing things the way you want them to be
designed. Sensu's flexible, one thing
well kind of philosophy makes that easy
but it also means that there's a lot of
components to learn and understand.
Hopefully you'll be able to work with me
and understand all these components
individually and then when we will bring them
all together you'll be able to
understand how they all operate as a whole.  For now though, let's deep dive and look at
each component and how it interacts and
really get a solid understanding about
how Sensu works at the architectural level.  To do that, I going to use the whiteboard and good
old-fashioned whiteboard markers to help you get that understanding.
So Sensu architecture.  Let's start with the Sensu Client.
The Sensu Client is the daemon or agent that runs on every server that you want to monitor.  It's written in
Ruby, so it can run on Linux, BSD, Windows.  The Client is the thing that actually
executes checks.  Checks are things like
the scripts that might be for checking
http or checking memory.  Now even though it runs on the Client, it doesn't necessarily
rule out the case where the Sensu Client is checking external resources.  So if
you have something outside, like Google, some switch or just something external, Sensu Client
can still check http or whatever you need it to do.  But where it really
shines is being able to check internal
things; this might be like memory or
processes or something like that.  In my
experience these are very common use cases for
monitoring systems to check internal things to a server.  The Sensu Client can
schedule its own checks, so it's on a
periodic timer.  So the Sensu Client
can be responsible for its own checks and
executing them on a timely fashion
it doesn't need the Sensu server to tell
it what to check and when.  These are
called "standalone" checks.  But don't worry about that for now, just be aware that
the Sensu Client could be totally
independent in this case.
But the Sensu Client can't act and
operate in a vacuum.  It needs someplace
to put the results of those checks,
that's RabbitMQ.  RabbitMQ serves as the
central message bus between Sensu
components.  And I know you might be thinking:
"Kyle, I came here to learn about Sensu, what does RabbitMQ have to do with any of this.  Is this yet
another technology I have to
learn?"  It's true that Sensu depends on
external component to do its message
passing and at first glance beginners might
think that this is an unnecessary burden
and it certainly increases the barrier
to entry on Sensu but long-term I
think you'll agree that not reinventing the
wheel and allowing an external component
that does its own thing really well is
essential for a long-term, scalable and
sustainable system.  Believe it or not, all
monitoring systems have some sort of
internal queue.  Sensu just happens to
not bother to reinvent that wheel and
it takes advantage of the awesome and
very reliable queue that is RabbitMQ.
So the Sensu Client connects to RabbitMQ
and outputs the results of the checks
that it executes.  Remember the Sensu Client is
the only component executes checks and
the Sensu Client only talks to RabbitMQ
and deposits the results of those
checks.  RabbitMQ provides a really good
separation between the Sensu Client
and other components.  It's a good seam.
The Sensu Client can continue to
operate on the checks, deposit results into
RabbitMQ completely independent of
all the other components; it just keeps
on ticking even if the Sensu server is
down your stuff is still being checked.
Next let's talk about the Sensu server.
The Sensu server is a daemon that
takes the results off of RabbitMQ and
operates on them.
The Sensu server executes "handlers"
based on the results of those checks.
Those "handlers" are scripts that take the
results of the check and operate on them.
They might be things like sending you an
email or talking to PagerDuty.
The Sensu server itself actually doesn't know anything about email, doesn't know anything about PagerDuty
doesn't know anything about
actually doing things with checks
other then sending them to the handlers for processing.  This is another thing that
makes Sensu a little hard to get into
because it doesn't have any kind of
native functionality for sending email out of
the box.
But again, long-term a system that doesn't burden itself with having to know how to send email
is a sustainable system.  It delegates
all the necessary plumbing to sending email
to a handler, like an email handler.  That does mean that out of the box it can't send email.
But that's ok.  You're taking this introductory course, I'll show you how to configure
Sensu to send email to you.  The Sensu
server also can do centralized
scheduling of checks.  Even though the
Sensu server doesn't actually execute
those checks it can ask Sensu Client to execute them on their behalf.
So it can put
onto RabbitMQ
that the Sensu Client is trying to pick up on, that
the Sensu Client will respond to.
Sensu Clients are tagged for certain
subscriptions.
The Sensu server might ask for a check HTTP to occur on all web servers.
Any Sensu Client that's been tagged with web
will up on that request, execute the check and put that check result back on the RabbitMQ.
These types of checks are called
"subscription" checks where as the previous one
where the Sensu Client was responsible for it's own checks on a timer
are "standalone" checks.  This gives you
the maximum flexibility for being able to
monitor things the way that you think
they should be monitored.  If you think that
the Sensu Client should be responsible
for all of its checks that's totally
legit or if you prefer the Sensu
server to have all the configuration
for what checks run on what servers you can do that too.  I personally prefer the
standalone checks only on Sensu
clients and I don't do any server-side
checks.  I find that gives me the most
flexibility because it allows me to use
a configuration management system to deposit the checks on the client
and only the clients that I determine in my
configuration management system to get
those checks get them, but it does
mean that I had to use a configuration
management system to orchestrate it. Server-side checks work well if you're kind of making those
checks by hand and you have well
formed tag's, your web servers are
well-defined.  Sometimes in the real world
it's not that clear cut.
But in Sensu, you can do it either way.  If you can believe it, the Sensu server, handlers
and the client are all stateless.  They
don't store any state and can be
scaled easily.  Sensu uses an external
component to store it states, that
component is Redis.  Redis is a general
key-value store that allows Sensu to
flexibly store any of its states that it needs
into some sort of persistent database.
Individual server components
don't store any of their state internally.
Any persistent state is
in Redis.
These are things like check history or which things are silenced and you might be thinking:
"well why is there yet another component, why can't Sensu just store it's own state internally?"
Well if you've ever built a
large scale web application you might
think to yourself that storing state is "evil" and in some sense it is.
Having Sensu store it's state in an external
database not only reduces the code complexity of
Sensu itself but also allows Redis
to do what it does well.
Having Sensu store it's state externally allows
the Sensu server component to be scaled
out.  By not storing it's state internally you
can have multiple Sensu servers all
using the same Redis and operating in
parallel to be able to operate on more
checks as they come in.
This gives the Sensu component's really good scaling properties and again it's one of those
only do one thing well kind of
philosophies where the Sensu server can
reuse the existing state-storing
goodness of Redis.  Would you believe that the
the Sensu server doesn't have any kind of
web component.  Again it comes down to that
one thing well philosophy. The Sensu server's only job is to take results from
RabbitMQ and operate on those handlers and then store the results in a long-term
results in Redis.  There's another
component
That serves the API front-end for Sensu.  It's just called the Sensu API.
The Sensu API talks with Redis and RabbitMQ and provides
a RESTful interface to the internals of
Sensu.  Its job is just to talk to these components
It also stores no state
and you can also scale it to run as many
API processes as you need to scale out
your infrastructure.
The Sensu API is what
empowers external applications to
integrate with Sensu.  For example: a dashboard or a CLI.
All they have to do is talk to the Sensu API.  They don't need to know anything about RabbitMQ or Redis.
They have a nice, well-defined RESTful interface to interact with.  That's an overview of the Sensu architecture.
I apologize for the terrible handwriting and white board.  If your organization's
like mine this is traditionally how
complicated systems are explained in real
life.  So I wanted to kind of emulate that with you
for better for worse.  As you can see
there's a lot of parts here.
Sensu was built with small components that do dedicated jobs.
It uses proven, existing solutions where possible to do the heavy lifting.
The end result is that as an engineer you have to understand all of these components as a whole.
If you ask me this is a good thing.
Where as more traditional monitoring systems treat all these components as a single whole,
one big black box, that you have no visibility into and no way to interact with directly.
Sensu splits these pieces out; you can scale them, individually you can query them directly
and you can integrate them with your
existing infrastructure.
It doesn't reinvent the wheel
and each component does one thing well To me this is really refreshing.
There's no single mega process that does
everything and each thing you can run multiples of
for high availability and scaling.  If you can appreciate the exploded
architecture and the one thing well
philosophy I think you'll find that
you'll never want to go back to a
situation where all of your monitoring
is handled under a single process that
if it dies nothing happens.
But the hard part is understanding each of these components and how they act and interact
together to make Sensu work.
But that's what this course is for.  To help explain how this works.
And don't fret, we'll cover each of these pieces and the dashboard and the Sensu handler
for sending email to give you a complete
system when you're done
that you could actually use to monitor things for real.  This is not an academic course.
This is an engineering course for building real systems that do real work.
If this overview is too fast or if my handwriting is too bad you can absolutely watch this lecture again!
Watch it as many times until you have a
feeling for how these components actually interact
Again, Sensu's architecture is one
of the more complex aspects Sensu
and it's essential for you to understand what's going on here
So feel free to review this as
needed.