In order to really look at why Sensu is worth looking at
let's look at the whiteboard and begin
to talk about how a normal monitoring system;
something more traditional might work.
I'm mostly going to be thinking about Nagios
in my head because that's
what I have a lot of experience with
but most centralized, traditional monitoring system work in the same way.
A more traditional monitoring system looks like this and then the centralized component packs all of this
into the server part, where the server is
responsible for: a dashboard, state, queue,
check execution and the server sends checks to host.  This is pretty normal
and what you might design if you were just building a monitoring system just from scratch.
But you'll quickly find that the architecture is limiting
because you can only check things that are externally accessible on this host
In order to get the inside scoop on what the host is doing internally
you have to run an agent and that
agent will do things in proxy for the server;
Things like: checking the RAID card
or seeing how much memory is on the host .
Things that are difficult to expose or things that you don't want to expose externally.
This is fine but why do we have to do this in the first place?
Well, that's because in traditional monitoring systems the server
schedules and executes the checks and the host doesn't really do anything, it just responds.
Whereas with Sensu the agent is the thing I execute the checks,
the server just responds to the results.
This is a big shift and a point that I
want to get across
as a key between Sensu and more traditional monitoring systems.
Again, in traditional monitoring systems the server executes the checks,
maybe via an agent but in Sensu, the Sensu client or agent executes all the checks,
Sensu server doesn't execute
anything. this allows things to scale.
A centralized monitoring system has to schedule and execute all the checks across all your systems.
If you have a hundred hosts and
hundred checks on each host
that means the server needs to execute
10,000 checks.
But with an architecture where the Sensu Client is responsible for executing it's checks,
the number of checks that you can execute scales with the number of hosts you have.
Each host is only responsible for executing
the checks on itself.
This is really the key to any scalable monitoring system.
And it's true that a lot of other monitoring systems can be re-architected to do this.
For example, Check_MK can be architected to do something similar,
but Sensu is designed from the ground up to be scalable.
The agent is responsible for all the check executions; the server just processes the results.
Another aspect of Sensu's architecture that I would like to point out
is this concept of client-side configuration.  In a traditional monitoring system,
all the check definitions are on the server. The server is responsible for things like:
check_web, ssh, memory, etc.  All of this
is configuration for the server.
In Sensu all of this can move to the client;
The client can know about what it's supposed to check: memory, web, ssh.
By moving the configuration from the
server to the client
you allow configuration management systems or deployment systems to deploy checks
with the application.  For example,
a configuration management system
or a deployment system can deploy a web
server and deploy the check for the web server
onto the same host.  In Sensu the server doesn't need to be updated
when new checks exist on clients at all.
The Sensu server doesn't care, it just
receives results.
When configuration is on the client it allows you to be more flexible
and allows you to deploy the checks in a more sane way.  No longer do you have to manually update
hostgroups on the server to correlate with deployments on the client.
To put it a different way, I like to to use the analogy between the map and the territory.
imagine that the configuration for your monitoring system is a map to the  things that are out there in real life.
A traditional monitoring system puts the burden of keeping this configuration in sync
on the system administrator, on the engineer.  But if the check configuration can be deployed with the host
the map of what checks exist on
which hosts
can more accurately represent the territory of what's in real life.
Let's put this analogy in more realistic terms. Let's say that you were using
Chef or Puppet or Ansible to deploy Apache.  In a more traditional monitoring system,
you would use Ansible to deploy Apache to the host
and then you would update the server to reflect you did that deployment to the host.
Remember, you're keeping the map up-to-date with the territory.
But what if you could deploy the monitoring with the application as a whole
directly on the host?  And now any server
that has Apache deployed to it
comes with a check_apache.
And then the Sensu (client) refreshes
and then starts checking
and sending the results of the check back the server.  The Sensu server doesn't have any configuration.
It doesn't know that there are now more web servers, it just responds the results.
It requires no configuration
changes on the Sensu server.
You might say that Sensu server's map is automatically updated with the real-life territory.
How about a different example?
Let's say that you're monitoring multiple hosts
and you add a new host.  Your territory
has now changed, you now have two hosts to check.
Who's going to remember to update
the server-side configuration
on a traditional monitoring system to start
monitoring that new host?
Well, either a tool or an engineer will have to keep that map up-to-date
with the new territory. It's gotta keep it in sync. But wait, in Sensu, the map and territory
are up-to-date already because as soon
as the Sensu Client on host #2
starts up, it automatically registers
itself with the Sensu server
Any checks associated with that hosts are
automatically deployed and start executing.
If you're using subscription-based checks that hosts will automatically start listening
for checks for the subscriptions that it has been configured to.
No Sensu server configuration changes when hosts are registered.
There is no configuration file for Sensu server that lists all the hosts that it's responsible for
because there is no such list.  Such a list would constantly be out-of-date.
Sensu is designed to accept new hosts on the fly
and deregister hosts when needed, at any
time with no configuration changes.
I hope my explanation between the map and the territory is sufficient.
It's kind of a hard idea to convey especially over a remote training session,
but if you can understand this difference in philosophy between
having the hosts responsible for updating
themselves in the Sensu server
contrasted to more traditional monitoring systems where an engineer or tool
is burdened with keeping the map, which is the configuration
up-to-date with the territory, which is what's out in real life.  You can see that this
this design decision allows the architecture itself to be conducive to host and checks coming in and out
at will.  Sensu enables this kind of automation by design.
Ready for the next kind of crazy idea?
Remember that in Sensu, the client
can have checks defined and it registers itself with the server components on the fly.
But what if I told you that you can enable new checks on the client
with no configuration changes and no restarting of the Sensu Client.
Analogous to how the Sensu Client dynamically registers itself with the Sensu infrastructure,
you can dynamically add new checks to the Sensu Client on the fly
The Sensu Client can receive check data for checks that don't even exist yet;
they can be dynamically generated.  Let's take a real-life example.
Let's say that you're hosting company and you serve many clients
and you have a dozen different customers.  And each customer has their own components.
Maybe they have their own website, their own webserver, maybe their own email server, who knows.
Heck, they may not even have their own server, maybe their own WordPress blog,
sky's the limit.
Let's say that you wanted a check for
every single component on the Sensu Client.
You might think that you need a file for each one
and every time there's a new customer you need to restart the Sensu Client.
You certainly could do that. But, you can write your own check,
Call it a "meta-check",
that's aware of these customers, iterates
through each one, checks them all individually
and then sends the results
directly to the Sensu Client.
It's check data that the Sensu Client didn't
execute itself,
we executed it with meta-check, maybe it's on a cron job,
that iterates over each client, each customer, sends the
results to the Sensu Client
and the Sensu Client in turn forwards it on to the Sensu infrastructure.
But the Sensu Client isn't configured with each customer
and new customers can be added on the fly in the meta-check will iterate over each one.
So nothing needs to change
on the Sensu Client at all.
New customers can exist or disappear, Sensu Client configuration donesn't change at all,
it just continues to forward on the results
of this meta-check on every execution.
Try to imagine doing this in a more
traditional monitoring tool; it'd be impossible.
You'd somehow have to connect the dots between all your customers and
the server components of your monitoring tool. But Sensu makes this really easy.
All you have to do is send JSON to localhost:3030. This is a very powerful idea
and it's kind of hard to convey again on a white board at an introductory course where everythingis brand new.
I just wanted to hint at this capability because it is such a powerful idea
that as far as I'm aware doesn't exist on any other monitoring system.
I hope this gives you a better idea of what makes Sensu unique and what makes it so powerful.
The key feature that I want to get across to you is that in Sensu
the territory of what servers are out there and what they have and what checks exist
is always in sync with the map that is the Sensu server configuration.
New hosts simply exist and register themselves.  New checks can exist on the client
and it's no big deal.  The Sensu server will receive data and operate on them as if they always existed.
I know for me personally I would never go back to another monitoring system
where it's up to the engineer to update the map that is the monitoring tool's configuration.
I would never go back to a world where there's a disconnect
between the monitoring configuration and the application.
In the end the key selling point to Sensu for me is the flexibility.
You can design systems with Sensu and have them monitor in ways that would be very difficult
or just impossible with more traditional,
centralized monitoring systems.
I hope this gives you a better idea of what
makes Sensu unique and different.
If this is all a blur, don't worry in the rest of
course, hopefully it will become more clear to you
how Sensu works and you'll learn more by
going through the actual exercises,
watching me configure the components and putting them together and eventually
everything will click when you go from an actual check that executes on the client
to an actual email in your inbox saying that something has failed or something has been resolved.