Hi.  My name is Kyle and I'm a systems
engineer and I run Sensu in production at
scale.  At the end of course you'll have a
fully working Sensu setup.  It'll be
actually checking things and actually
sending you emails when things are broken.
We'll also cover how to use the dashboard
and how to take advantage of the Sensu
community plug-ins; a huge repo of open
source plugins that's ready to be
integrated with Sensu with a single
command.  And guess what?
Learning a new system is all about
making mistakes.  In this course I'm
actually gonna purposely make mistakes,
go through the act of actually
troubleshooting them and then fix them right
in front of you.  That way you know what
it looks like when things are broken and
what it looks like when they're
fixed.  This course is specifically
designed for curious DevOps-y style
engineers who are looking to better
their craft.  So enroll today and learn
about what makes Sensu special with
me.