Welcome to lecture on installing Sensu itself.
Now that we have the requisite components RabbitMQ and Redis installed, now it's time to install Sensu proper.
As before I'm gonna be following the official documentation on how to do this
which I recommend you do as well for your first
time after all this is an introductory
course. Sensu is convenient in the sense that it provides its own repositories make it
easier to stay up to date. So let's install those repos...
Now we have the repositories we can
actually install sensu...
As an engineer, you need to know that Sensu is deployed via an "omnibus" package. What that
means is that the package itself
contains every file it needs to run
including its own Ruby interpreter. Let's
take a look at the package and see what
files it has...
Some.. "/etc" files...
Some.. shared... but most of it is going to be in
"/opt/sensu", and a lot of it in the "embedded" folder.
This is the embedded Ruby interpreter and all the gems that Sensu requires
to run, including the components necessary to run the sensu-api, the sensu-server
sensu-client. That doesn't mean that you have to run each of these components it's just
deployed as a single package: you can
just start the client or just start the
server whatever components you need. But they're all available if you need them. This package is
large but it makes it very easy to
deploy Sensu on platforms which may
not have an up-to-date version of Ruby.
Using the omnibus package you get to take advantage of this this consistent
version of Ruby that you can deploy on
any distro and be confident it's gonna work
regardless of how old that distro is, or new? It's very convenient. The embedded
Ruby also gives you some additional
benefits when deploying plugins and
writing your own "handlers". We'll talk about that in later lectures.
Let's take a look at the configuration
files because as an engineer you spend a
lot of time configuring things. Sensu has a conf.d-style directory where you
can fill it up with files.
Let's take a look at this Readme...
All of Sensu's configuration files are JSON. JSON is a machine readable format.
It's not really designed for humans to be
editing although you can read them as a
human and you can edit them as a human. It's best to use a program to deploy these like a
configuration management tool like Chef or Puppet. It's outside the scope of this
introductory class so we're gonna be
kinda editing these files by hand, but
you need to know that they are JSON
files so they are very vulnerable to
typos and trailing commas. Let's go
back to the docs and see what we should
do next.
Let's get this kind-of "getting started"
configuration file...
You can see the docs recommend we deploy that in this config.json right here in /etc/sensu. Let's
look at it...
These options are required to let Sensu know where to discover all of these
requisite components: RabbitMQ and Redis that we setup before and of course that API. You can see they all
point to localhost. Which is fine. For this introduction class all of these
components are running on the same
server. You can imagine later if you
scale out your components, you might put
RabbitMQ, Redis, and the API on one set of
servers and then the clients will be
different, but they'll need to point to
those RabbitMQ, Redis, and API servers.
Back in the official docs: the first thing they recommend is installing a check. So let's do that...
You can see that put that in 'conf.d'. In
reality it doesn't really matter about
the directory structure in this folder
because they always get merged together.
This makes it really easy for
configuration management tools to add
components, configuration pieces one file
at a time and get them all merged
together when Sensu reloads. But for humans it's kinda nice to have
one check per JSON.
Now the docs say that we've installed this configuration
for a check but we haven't actually installed this check yet. You can see the path we
haven't put this here yet, but we will soon.
Next the docs recommend we install some sort of "handler",  so let's do that.
If you remember from the architecture diagram "handlers"
are these scripts that Sensu uses to
respond to events. This might be things like
interacting with the PagerDuty API, sending you an email.. This "handler" is very simple. It's
a pipe "handler" which means it takes
standard in. The command we are running as "cat".
You can imagine, "cat" with this handler is
not gonna do much except just spit out
whatever it got on the "standard in". We'll see how that actually works a bit later when we
look at the logs.
So we have our our "check_men", we have our "cat" handler.
Now we're going to go ahead and start the server components...
We've started the sensu-server and the sensu-api.
Let's go ahead and take a look at the log for the
sensu-server and sensu-api now that we've started them. The logs are were you might expect them
"/var/log/sensu". We have two logs since we've started those two things. Let's look at the api..
You may notice this is a little hard to read.  This is in JSON as well. This makes it a little harder for humans to
read but does make it easy for machines
and log aggregators like Logstash to
consume. If you're working with a lot of JSON, I kind of recommend using this tool
called "jq".
jq is a tool to parse JSON and
do fancy things with it.
The closest analogue I could think of is
it's like "sed",  but instead of plaintext it works with
JSON. As you saw the sensu-api.log is just full of, it's just all JSON. You can pipe that
to jq and the "." command and just prints
things. It makes it a little easier to read but no big deal.
We'll look at these logs later in more depth.
Let's take a look at the sensu-server log..
If you look carefully, you can see that it's already publishing check requests for that
memory check that we installed. Now we haven't setup any clients yet so nobody's
responding, but the Sensu server is
scheduling these checks to be executed.
That's all for this lecture on the Sensu server components. We'll cover setting up
the Sensu client and the next lecture.