So far in this course we've been using this
toy "check_mem"
in the tutorial from the official documentation just for
tinkering with.
Let's see if we can do something a little more realistic and useful.
You know, not everybody has the luxury of setting up a green-field monitoring system.
Let's say they that you are migrating from Nagios
and you want to reuse the existing check definition and plugins
that you're already using in your
infrastructure.
I think this is great; I love reusing components.
Let's download the Nagios plugins.
Let's see where they are.
let's get this check disk a try...
Ok. So far my disk is OK. I'm gunna actually create a "ballast" file that I can  use to simulate what
it would be like if I filled up the disk. Ok, I
created a ballast file to simulate what it
would be like if I had a full disk. I've
gotten the check_disk plugin to actually
fail at 20%. let's use this check,
and actually configure in Sensu and
see if we can make it email us.
Now, I don't want to re-use this check_memory.json
I kinda wanna leave it just there. Let's
make a new configuration file from scratch,
and we'll populate it with the check for
check_disk
It's a JSON dictionary, if you read the
official documentation on how to make
these check definitions. It's like this:
And all we have to do is fill in the check right here:
Let's call it: "check_slash"
Let's make the command the commander we ran.
Now we get to decide if this is going to be a
stand-alone check or a subscription
check. Remember that stand-alone checks
are defined and scheduled by the client.
Subscription checks are defined and scheduled
by server. I like standalone-checks myself. And disks are kinda one of those things
that are kind of intrinsic to a server,
sort of? So let's pretend that we're going
to deploy these checks with either
configuration management or through a provisioning
tool, or even my hand. But by using a
stand-alone check, we can define our check_slash
definition differently on every single
host,  as different host might have
different thresholds or might have
different disks to check, and that kind of thing.
Stand-alone checks can be defined by
simply saying "standalone":  true
And if you are going to define a standalone check, you need at least an interval. This is how often the check
will run.
It's in seconds, so for testing I'm gonna pick 10 seconds. If you haven't spotted the typo already,
I need a trailing comma on this entry,
and I need no trailing coma on this entry.
Just in case
let's check our work with "jq"...
Looks ok. It's not that
bad. The configuration is designed to be
made by a machine. JSON is a machine format,
it's not very forgiving. But you can
work through it and with "jq" it's
easy to check for syntax before you go
restarting the Sensu client. Because this
is a standalone check, the only thing we
have to restart here is this is the sensu-
client itself. Let's go ahead and do that..
And now tail the logs...
Now that we have a number of checks this log is getting a little hard to read. But here's the output:
It is running the command we asked it to. It is coming back critical. Well, do we have any mail?
We do!
Our host is out of disk space.
Let's clear out that ballast file and
see if it fixes it.
We're gonna sneak a peak at the log again...
And it already came back OK.
Let's check our mail again.
There's our resolve.
So there you have it.
We used an existing Nagios plugin, no
problem. We made our check definition.
We made a stand-alone check this time: A
check that is scheduled and defined on the client only.
And we got very fast feedback with an interval of 10 seconds. Now let's say that
you were not content with the old-fashioned Nagios plugins and you wanted
to try something new from the community
plugins repo. Maybe something that
catches your eye and you think: oh I really
want some RabbitMQ checks.
So you go look for them.. and there's a package for you.
And looks at all these checks. By all means, take advantage of the existing work that's been open sourced
for you to use! Let's see if we can install
this rubygem and take advantage of it.
Let's remind ourselves where the embedded Sensu Ruby lives...
To refresh your memory, Sensu comes with the embedded Ruby that we can use to install these plugins.
Alternatively you could use the
existing system installed Ruby, but I
like to use embedded Ruby because it comes with something for free. We'll run "gem
install sensu-plugins-rabbitmq". We do
have to run this with "sudo" because all
these files are owned by root. Now that it's installed let's look at that "bin"
folder again and see if we have anything
new. ls /opt/sensu/embedded/bin/ | grep rabbitmq
And you can see that we have
some new checks here that we can run.
Let's give a "alive" one shot....
RabbitMQ is alive. Let's see it fail.
"Critical"
Let's make a check definition...
Again Sensu doesn't really mind how
you organize your files, because it does
one big merge. As long as we setup these in the "checks" dictionary, it will work.
We at least have to specify the command.
We'll make this one a stand-alone check.
And again let's try the interval of "10".
Let's check our work with "jq"
It's fine. Now we restart the sensu-client to pick it up...
And look, there's a failure! I've made a very common mistake, something that happens
all the time again, it's very easy to
make mistakes when you're writing checks
out by hand. It's very likely that you'll encounter a similar situation. Can
spot my typo from here?
Nope! Neither can I!
Let's take a look at the logs...
Sensu is not running because we have an invalid configuration file.
The error is a little cryptic:
Check subscribers must be an array. The fact that it's looking for subscribers, hints that Sensu is
interpreting this check as a "subscription check" and not a "standalone"
check. With that data maybe you can spot
the error now?
That's right, "standalone" is misspelled.
Let's try again...
It is running our check. Now what will happen if I actually stop RabbitMQ?
Can the Sensu client operate with RabbitMQ stopped?
The answer is "no", it cannot.
But let's start it back up again...
Sensu does reconnect and continues to operate. Because Sensu depends
on RabbitMQ you're not going to able to
monitor directly like this. When RabbitMQ
is down this, the Sensu client can't
connect to it, and therefore can't
deposit the check results of RabbitMQ
being down. This can make it difficult to
check Sensu itself. In later more
advanced courses I'll cover how to
monitor Sensu as a whole, for a more
production environment. What
notifications to get after we stopped
RabbitMQ? If the Sensu client wasn't
able to report that RabbitMQ was down,
What notifications did we actually
get? Look at this: this a keepalive warning
and a "resolve" that the keepalive was "ok".
Let's look at the email...
"No keepalive was sent from the client for 121 seconds."
"Greater than the threshold of 120". This is how the Sensu-server knows when a client has stopped
responding. Clients periodically send
heartbeats onto RabbitMQ for the server to
pick up on. And when they stop sending
heartbeats, that's when the server knows
that his client is no longer available.
So when RabbitMQ went down there was no
way to the Sensu client to send
heartbeats, and the Sensu server picked
up on that, and spawned an alert. It is an
interesting side effect to stopping
RabbitMQ. So when you're deploying
Sensu and you see these alerts, now you
know what they mean. It doesn't mean that the Sensu server can't talk to the Sensu
client, at least not directly. It means that the client can't talk to the queue. And we caused
that to happen here when I stopped RabbitMQ. So just FYI
an interesting side effect of our testing.
That's it for adding more checks. Feel free
to look at the extra resources of this
course to see the
official documentation on the correct
syntax for how to define checks with Sensu,
and the show notes for all the commands I used in this lecture. Till
then I hope you've got a better idea of
how to make checks in Sensu, how to
reuse your existing Nagios plugins. Or take advantage of the many community
plugins on github. As you can see the checks we wrote are real. they're doing real work,
and Sensu is making a real alert emails because of them.