Welcome to the lecture on installing the
Sensu Client.
If you recall, previously we installed installed Sensu server, Sensu API,
we also setup Redis and RabbitMQ.
Now we're ready to actually set up a Sensu Client that will actually execute checks,
respond to them and show up in the API and dashboard. Let's do that now.
We already have the package installed.
Remember it's an omnibus package; there's not a separate Sensu Client
package to install so we can
use that same Sensu omnibus package,
but we need some configuration. So let's do that now.
You can see that put the configuration into /etc/sensu/conf.d/
And it's this "client.json".
If you look at that just a little bit some important things to note:
Name is the name of the client, "test"  from boilerplate from the docs.
Let's fill this in with something a little fancier.
The address is free-form as far as I know
Remember that the Sensu Client's job is to put results on to the RabbitMQ host.
So as long as it can connect to RabbitMQ
there doesn't need to be actual any TCP communication between the client and server.
RabbitMQ serves as the bridge
between the two,
so they could even be on separate networks and it won't really matter.
Subscriptions represent the lists of tags that this client will respond to.
If you recall "test" is the same tag that we assigned that check
when we configured the server
with the check_mem.
So because the check_mem is going to be associated with a certain "test" tag
and our client will subscribe to that test tag,
our client should be using that check memory thing that the Sensu server is exporting.
Now that we have that client installed, let's go ahead and get the check-mem.sh command.
If you recall from our architecture diagram the Sensu Client is the only thing that actually execute checks.
In this example we have the Sensu server and Sensu client on the same machine,
but if the Sensu Client was on a
different machine
the actual check scripts only need to exist on that client.
and just in case, we need to make everything readable by Sensu.
Now we're ready to actually start
this client.
Let's see if it is running.
You can see that on this box, because we have the same
pieces of infrastructure. We have the Sensu server running from before, and the Sensu API.
And now we have this client running, we just started it up.
Let's take a look at the logs.
You can probably guess where they are by now.
See it started up, loaded some configuration and
here you can see it actually received some check requests.
These are coming from the server based
on those tags that we issued, the test tag.
Here the client is actually publishing the result of that check.
you see that it's coming up: "MEM OK - free system memory 256 MB".
So the Sensu Client is responding to these check requests
and the publishing the check
results back on the RabbitMQ for processing.
That's all the client does is execute checks and put the results on the RabbitMQ.
And you can see it's already doing that based on the configuration files we've given it.
Let's go ahead and make sure it will start on boot.
You can see that the Sensu Client package is part of the same
Sensu omnibus package.  So installing our remote host will pretty much be
the same thing
except they also need that one configuration file for connecting to RabbitMQ.
Remember RabbitMQ is the only thing that the Sensu client needs to connect to be useful.
We got away with reusing the exact
same RabbitMQ configuration file we had already,
but that was in this: "config.json" here.
But if you were installing more Sensu clients you at the very least need this piece of configuration data
available to those remote Sensu Clients so they know where to put the results of their checks.
and where to listen to for new check requests.
"localhost" will be different in that case because the remote Sensu Client on different hosts
won't be connecting to "localhost" for their RabbitMQ they'll be connecting to some sort of
shared RabbitMQ. In theory, this server wherever the RabbitMQ is running.