Welcome to Tinkering with Uchiwa.
If you're installing Sensu for the first time then this dashboard is going to be brand new to you,
so I want to show you around a bit.
As a reminder the Uchiwa dashboard is the open-source dashboard
there's also the enterprise dashboard but it operates very much the same way.
In fact the enterprise dashboard is based on Uchiwa at source code level.
Notice on this first landing page here,
is there anything in particular that you notice about it?
Maybe something that's not here?
It may surprise you, but a very common misunderstanding about Sensu is that
it is not a "green light" dashboard.
What that means is:
Sensu by default is not going to show you all of the hundreds or thousands or
millions of checks that are green in your infrastructure.
The reasons for this are somewhat technical and somewhat philosophical
but the core problem is that green light dashboards, in general, don't scale very well.
Sensu's event-driven architecture means that it only shows you the things that are red.
This is in general a good thing.
It is true that Sensu does record the event output of green
checks but by default it doesn't show up on the event page.
Let's talk a little bit more about this
this landing page here.
We're on the Events section of Uchiwa.
Notice here, this "Source" column
You can sort it if you want to but it's "hostname".
This is because Sensu can actually accept events for hosts that don't even exist.
This is especially helpful for things like:
network gear, switches, PDUs, clusters or kinda like, meta-hosts.
Although it's an advanced topic, that's
what this is for.
Now this next column, "Check", you see the actual check name.
Here would be the output of the check if I had one.
For this demonstration I just made these checks up, I didn't actually output
any output here so you don't see anything.
Here's where you might see something like:  "OK: 100 MB FREE" or something like that.
This column here is "Occurrences"
This is the number of times that this check has come back red or has been failing.
Sensu doesn't record the number of times that it's been "ok".
Again it's part of that green light dashboard thing; it only records failing checks like this.
All of these have a number "1" meaning
when I made them I just made them one so they haven't reoccurred.
So there's only been one occurrence of each of these checks.
This column here is "Datacenter".
Remember that Uchiwa is capable of showing your multiple data centers at the same time.
We just have one datacenter for our demonstration so it's just "localhost".
This column here is "Issued"
This is when the actual check came in.
As you can see they came in at different times when I executed them,
but it's helpful to be able to sort these to see what are the most recent, failing checks.
Let's click on an event and see more data.
You can see in this model we have  some more data about the host that made it
and the event output.
This speaker icon here is for silencing the host,
and this speaker icon here is for silencing the check itself.
Most Sensu handlers will also suppress the notifications for a check if the host is silenced.
One subtle thing here is that handlers do have to be silenced-aware.
When we did the very simple "cat" handler, if you remember from our basic installation,
the "cat" handler doesn't know anything about silences so it's going to continue to run cat continuously.
Take a look at this "X" here, this Delete.
What do you think it means to "Delete" a client?
I'll talk about it a bit more when we get to the client section
How about this checkmark?
"Resolve" What does it mean to resolve a check?
Well, in Sensu because it's all event-driven
you can actually resolve any check that comes in yourself.
In fact, I'll click it right now.
It's been resolved!
However, if the thing that emitted the event in the first place
for example Sensu Client or Cron job or
something that was emitting this event
is still failing, you'll see this come back red.
once again, and it will re-notify you.
But sometimes it happens that events are
one-time things or they can be spawned ephemerally,
and human or via API might need to manually resolve these.
Let's move on to clients.
Looks very similar to the "Event" page
except it's more client-based.
We can see all the unique clients that I have set up.
Again some of these are fake and setup for demonstration purposes.
If you recognize "mycoolhost" is what I called
the original host that we setup so this one's actually real.
Let's check out "mycoolhost"
You can silence a host by clicking this volume icon again
It'll ask you for how long you want it to be silenced,
Let's say 24 hours and say: "Doing A Demo"
We'll talk about "stashes" in a bit. You can see this has changed to a muted icon.
Again, depending on the handler and most handlers will do this,
they'll suppress the alerts for these as well since the host has been silenced.
Remember this "Delete" button here?
Let's go ahead and click it.
The client has been deleted.
But wait!  It's still here.
Oh wait it's gone.
And now it's back.
What happened was, it took a second or two for the host to actually disappear from the dashboard
then a second or two later "mycoolhost" reregistered itself with Sensu.
The act of deleting a client,
while it did delete the client for a few moments,
the client is very much still alive and still
emitting event data
and it's registering itself in Sensu continuously.
Hopefully this is getting the gears in your imagination turning for
how useful this would be in a dynamic environment.
Remember all of this is happening through the API
or there are also good command line
tools.
So just think about what you could build with a system where
you don't have to tell it what hosts exist or don't exist;
they can come and go and register
themselves
But you saw that me deleting the client didn't actually make it go away permanently.
Remember that metaphor that I mentioned before about the map and the territory?
Sensu is always in a continuous state of making the map
more accurate to what's actually out there in the territory.
If that makes any sense.
Let's take a look at checks.
The checks in this check modal only show server-side checks.
The Sensu API can't really be aware of
the stand-alone checks that are
only defined on the clients.
This is a little bit confusing to newcomers because it looks like
only a subset of their checks are defined.
That's because you're only seeing the checks on the server.
There may be hundreds and thousands of
checks that are defined
in unique ways on each client. And their all responsible for executing those checks
and submitting the results, but the Sensu server doesn't know about them so they don't show up in this modal.
This screen is actually read-only there's
nothing you can actually do with these checks; it's just informational.
Let's look at the next section: "Stashes"
Stashes are Sensu's freeform key value store.
The Sensu handlers can use the stashes however they need to.
For example, we made a stash a few seconds ago by silencing this host.
Our Sensu handlers can pick up
on the fact that this stash exists
and then choose not to emit any emails or not talk to the PagerDuty API
depending on whether this stash exists.
But stashes are just key/values; you can use them for anything,
but silencing is the most popular way to use them.
Remember there's just an API for this.
So what if you imagined that you had a provisioning system that launches new hosts?
And then you want them to be silenced for a few hours just because they just came up.
Can you imagine making that API call or using a CLI tool with such a provisioning system?
In the "Reason" field you might say something like say something like "Silencing because it just came up"
And the "Source" might be your provisioning tool.
Could be pretty cool.
The "aggregate" section is an advanced topic.
I'm not going to talk about aggregates much in this introductory course;
they have to do with executing one
particular check over the course of many hosts
and then doing a tally or an aggregation of those results and acting on it.
This would be useful for something like
checking http over the course of a large fleet of web servers.
Again, it's more of an advanced topic but,
we can talk about it in more advanced courses.
The "Datacenter" screen
Here would be the list of data centers that you defined in Uchiwa
and all of them and they're connected states.
You can see we only have one datacenter, just our localhost,
but it is connected.
It has some events,
has a few clients,
one check,
and some stashes.
That's about it for the dashboard.
Uchiwa is a modern dashboard, very responsive and it gets the job done.
This is just an introductory course,
but if you imagine there's a lot more that you could be doing.
Uchiwa actually will automatically embed
links and images
to give you a really rich experience if you want to embed graphs from an external data source.
And of course, don't forget the API.
The dashboard is just a convenient way for humans  to interact with the API using a web browser
To give you know another example of how to use the API,
take a look at this script I have on GitHub to spit out the status and events for a particular host.
You can see the first time I ran this it had all those checks that were failing.
Then when we deleted the host
we cleared it out
and now its silenced, everything is green.
This is interacting with the same API that Uchiwa is interacting with,
but you can see the possibilities are opened up because it's machine readable
and we can use it for many more interesting things.
Can you imagine putting this in the
message of the day
so when you log in to your server you see right away if there any failing checks for it?
Also could be pretty cool.
But, for now that's Uchiwa: the open-source Sensu dashboard and how it works.